# Christopher Hamm

Lead Data Scientist

Carmichael, CA 95608 USA butterflyology@gmail.com butterflyology.github.io

# Summary

Lead Data Scientist with a strong research and experimental background and 10+ years experience using reproducible methods and rigorous analysis to generate unique insights and create value. Strong teacher using research-based pedagogy and a Software Carpentry Foundation Trainer.

# Experience

2022-Present Lead Data Scientist, Nestlè Purina - Data Analytics.

Kyle Herrman, supervisor.

#### Technical Leadership

- Created linear optimizer that saved \$600,000/month in shipping costs
- Created Sales Anomaly Detector to ensure continuous profitable growth
- Mentored new hire and intern data scientists

2018–2022 Lead Data Scientist, Bayer - Decision Science.

Nalini Polavarapu, supervisor.

# Technical Project Management:

- Supervised 30+ statistical projects
- Led a team of Data Scientists and Educators
- Develop, promote, and distribute best practices curriculum for enterprise data scientists
- Develop proprietary curriculum for company specific workflows
- Created neural network forecasting models for supply chain

#### Mentorship & Training:

- Platinum Pinnacle Award for creating and implementing company-wide digital fluency
- Organize, coordinate, mentor, and teach data fluency workshops instructing over 1500 learners in 8 programming languages/programs across 55 workshops
- Coordinate 44 digital fluency trainers

#### • Member:

- Data Science Center of Excellence
- Model Governance Team
- Data Management Team

#### 2017–2018 **Data Scientist**, *Monsanto Company*.

Shawn L. Stricklin, supervisor.

#### Individual Contributor:

- Developed and implemented a program to simulate the vegetable breeding pipeline
- Implemented predictive modeling to predict genotype sample submission frequency
- Created gradient boosted regression model to identify disease susceptible genotypes
- Provided ad hoc statistical support to 10 plant breeders
- Organized and coordinated Software Carpentry and Instructor Training workshops

# 2016–2017 Postdoctoral researcher, University of California, Davis.

C. Titus Brown, supervisor.

Achievements:

 Oversaw development and deployment of Reproducible Research with R lessons for the Data Carpentry Foundation

# 2014–2016 Postdoctoral scholar, University of Kansas.

James R. Walters, supervisor.

Achievements:

- Developed tools to analyze large empirical and simulated molecular datasets
- Implemented and interpreted complex statistical modeling on ecological and genomic data, including differential expression analysis
- Formalized novel statistical models to describe bacterial infection frequency while correcting for relatedness

# 2012–2014 Postdoctoral researcher, University of California, Davis, Davis, California.

David J. Begun and Michael Turelli, supervisors.

Achievements:

- Coordinated multi-laboratory effort to assess the use of a bacterial infection to control an invasive insect
- Executed comparative genomic analysis of invasive species
- Created bioinformatics pipeline to import, trim, and map genomic data

# Education

- 2012 PhD, Michigan State University, Entomology.
- 2012 PhD, Michigan State University, Ecology, Evolutionary Biology & Behavior.
- 2008 MS, California State University, Fresno, Biology.

With Distinction

2004 BS, California State University, Fresno, Biology.

Magna Cum Laude

# Statistical methods

Deep learning in R & Python using Keras and TensorFlow

Deep learning in python with pytorch and fastai

Machine learning in R & python

Linear and mixed-effects models in R

Forecasting with ARIMA, prophet, and LSTM

Hierarchical Bayesian modeling and inference in R and stan

# Computer skills

Data analysis R, Python

Reproducibility docker, knitr, RMarkdown, LATEX, jupyter notebooks,

Cloud AWS ML Pipeline & SageMaker, Applied AI with IBM Watson, MS Azure computing

Misc. git, GitHub, BASH, SQL